We want like the juicy stuff.
What do you think about this thing, right?
And his answer was yes.
A very small group of people actually understand the meaning of money.
So I think you're the perfect person to ask this question.
Finance exists because the people that actually have the money
are not necessarily the same people that have good ideas on how to spend it,
on how to use it.
You increase your allocation to bonds on leverage,
so you're amplifying the bonds return.
And what that does is, yes, part of your portfolio is levered up,
but actually your risk is lower.
The average company in the S&P 500 is his levered itself, 2x.
This is the part where we say it's not investment advice.
I'm bullish Bitcoin, but I'm not bullish Bitcoin in the next year.
So crypto is clearly a risky asset.
So we are not really there yet.
The inflation is still quite high.
People talk about ETFs, but really it's not open to retail yet.
It's not.
If you are like a retail investor and you are in America
and you want to ape in, I'm not in crypto to make 10%.
What is your personal investment strategy for this bull run?
When you look at your wealth, right?
You should invest 80% or 90% of that into a beta portfolio.
10% to 20% just do alpha.
I don't like to pick things that I don't understand.
The entire world's biggest fund of the fund and fund fund
is to think of the fund and fund fund
not only look at the fund
but also look at the fund
and look at the kind of tools to help
you may have heard of it
but they actually
are they doing what they do?
Today, the guest of the first time is very happy
because he was in the world's most expensive
of the fund
Ray Dalio's next to the
The
Now he will take the
the most detailed
of the
the
But I want to remind you
this video
of the
very
and try to test your financial skills
If you don't understand
you may have to look at it
You will have to learn
many very stupid
basic tools
Hello! Hi everyone!
You used to work in traditional finance, right?
What exactly that you did?
I worked for a hedge fund called Bridgewater Associates
I know people might have heard of Ray Dalio
I worked in his company in research
which is kind of like the department where he worked
So I worked there as a financial engineer
like an analyst
for about like five years
I was in the credit team
during the European financial banking crisis
So we were like doing like models
and indicators and so on
for like Eurozone aggregate stuff
Like why were things happening
the way they were happening?
What would happen in the future
if a bunch of things, you know, rolled out
and nobody we thought they would?
Then after that I launched a robo advisor
in a fintech company
which arguably didn't go too well
but it was a cool concept
It was around essentially, you know,
democratizing an investment
a passive long-term investment strategy
called risk parity
for everyday investors
and then Silicon Valley as a product manager
also in fintech for several years
before essentially I entered venture into the world of crypto
Wow, that is a crazy resume you got right there
Okay, let's go back to the traditional finance
because recently there's this TikTok video
that went viral
It's like, you know, there's this girl says
I'm looking for a man in finance
I don't know if you've seen that
with trust fund
6'5, blue eyes
Well, my question is
is there like a hierarchy in this world?
For example, like bankers, investment bankers, like
who looked down on who?
We want like the juicy stuff
Besides the income part of it
which is probably like why?
Yeah, I mean, so things might have changed
but when I was working there
I would tell you
I would definitely, definitely
the number one in the hierarchy
in the dating situation, you know
I would be an investment banker, right?
If you were working for an investment bank
you were, surprise, surprise
making the most money during that time
imagine the investment banker, like this super alpha male
like double squared alpha male kind of guy
Wolf of Wall Street
Yeah, yeah, but buff, right?
And then you ask yourself
the thing I always ask myself is like
where do these guys find time to work out?
They're like working like 100 hours a week, right?
That's the guy, that's the figure, right?
Below that, I would say like
I mean, maybe at the same level
but a little bit below like hedge fund guys
specifically managers and so on
Where do you see crypto bros fit in in this hierarchy?
It's a good question
I don't know, it's maybe
a little bit of a controversial answer as well
It depends on kind of like
what the girl is attracted to, right?
Is it like super alpha, strong, you know
like dominant men, right?
And then you go traditional finance
investment banking
is a more of a beta kind of guy
that has a ton of money and is super nerdy
then maybe you go for crypto
I would say hyper generalizing things
What was your crypto journey like?
How did you become the CEO of Mars Protocol Foundation?
But when I was working at Bridgewater
actually most of 2013
basically I learned about Bitcoin
and I actually went to the dev like a team
which is called the FX team
that just works on currencies
and I went to them and I said
and I went to a specific guy
I'm not gonna say his name
pretty high up there
and I said
what do you think about this thing, right?
And his answer was
I don't know if I can curse here
but it was
the real answer was it's BS
I should not say the full word
and the reason why it's BS
he gave me the reasons, right?
Which to be honest were pretty valid reasons
but were kind of short-sighted
But to be honest
I kind of agreed with him
on most of what he was saying
They were thinking about it as like
an alternative to a currency
and Bitcoin has pretty much
almost no property of a currency
It has more properties of a store of value
which is a little different right now
because I was very dogmatic
about this thing
But I kept monitoring it
because it's got all these problems
Over time
what I learned is like
with technology and with human will
you actually do solve problems
and if you put
throw money at it
you put like really good people at it
you actually solve problems
and eventually like
Ethereum came
and became programmable, right?
On Ethereum
And then the next thing that came
was decentralized stablecoins, right?
With the Terra
arguably massive epic failure of UST, right?
Luna
But that was kind of like the moment
for me, okay, okay
I've been proven wrong on these things
that actually had
actually occurred
This is really exciting
This is really what I want to be doing
And that's kind of like
when I made that kind of lead, right?
And I joined Delphi Labs
Let's take a step back
because I feel like
a lot of people in crypto
they're trying to redefine finance
and a very small group of people
actually understand the meaning of money
So I think you're the perfect person
to ask this question
What is the meaning of money?
I think there's just two levels
to this question
There's a practical meaning of money
Money is really an
and a medium exchange
that is actually simple to use
meaning it's like
there's all these properties, right?
I'm just giving you a bunch
like it's not
it's not like difficult to transfer
It's all, you know
like it can be split as a smaller fraction
One important principle
is that it doesn't change value
too much for a time
It's called something inflation
It's a little bit of predictable inflation
And the value of that
is really that
what's the value?
Is that people can actually
do different jobs
and do and you know
like and they generate value
in a specific way
They can kind of like
that value is represented
all can be all represented
in this kind of like
medium of exchange
and therefore like
you know if I do something
and I'm not selling you
the service of what I do
I can be paid in a medium exchange
I can actually use for something else
Right?
For example like
you know if I'm a plumber
and you don't need plumbing
but I need to buy fruit from you
I get paid in this medium of exchange
and then I pay you the fruit
Right?
It's kind of like the value
right?
The practical value
and meaning of money
But there's really a second level
to this question
It's like
what does it really mean
to have money?
I think it's more of a psychological question
and assuming that the money
that you actually accumulate
translates in wealth
meaning it doesn't depreciate
too much in value
and that there are very limited
externally imposed ways
to not allow you to spend it
I'm not going to talk about countries
that have that
So capital restrictions
you know
overtaxing and all that stuff
Right?
Then money
money can actually equal freedom
Freedom because ultimately
you have control over your life
and it gives you options really
to decide how do you spend your money
to do what you want
So with that explanation
the next question will be
what is finance?
Why does it exist?
I'll give you like the one sentence
and then I can expand on it
a little bit
Finance exists
because the people that actually
have the money
are not necessarily the same people
that have good ideas
on how to spend it
on how to use it
in a way that's virtuous for society
That's really the concept
behind finance
In its pure original form
If I have money
and it isn't depreciating
a little bit over time
but that's not necessarily an incentive
I kind of want to give it
to someone else
that can actually make my money increase
and that person
that doesn't have money
but has a really good idea
maybe wants to invent
the next you know
quantum computing thing
right?
He doesn't have the money
So he needs to get it
right?
So you essentially
give it to that person
and so what you're doing
is you're taking some risk
you're giving it to that person
who is essentially
going to use the money
to invent something
that society potentially needs
and therefore increase
that money
and give you back
your part plus some amount
and keep the other amount
himself becoming richer
you increasing your wealth
essentially being paid
for the risk that you took
and overall
in creating this virtuous
like growth in the economy
and where essentially
everybody can benefit
and the overall
average wealth increases
right?
Because this guy has invented
something that's useful
and has made our life better
and that incentive
is the interest rate
if you don't
if you cannot charge
an interest rate
you're not going to be
incentivized to take risk
so the question
and the question is
like how much is that
and the riskier that your investment is
then now how you need to be compensated
for that risk
yeah that's a very perfect example
and you talk about leverage
in one of your videos
when people hear the word leverage
people always think
oh we're talking about
like trading on crypto exchanges
50x 100x
and you get liquidated
it's dangerous
it's risky right
i can't say they're wrong
but a lot of times
there are a lot of common practices
that people see
and they don't even realize
those are leverages
what is your definition
of leveraging
the way i define leverage
and it's just not just me right
but it's it's just the tool
to amplify risk
which results essentially
in a potential higher
return or a higher loss
so you amplify your risk
by you know taking more risk
but why do you do that
because potentially you can make more
in the same way you can lose more
to get the other part of the question
so like yes you can think of leverage
taking like a crazy crypto 50x 100x
that is basically gambling right
you're gambling right
you're extreme gamble
but that's not the only way
first of all most professional traders
actually don't do 50x
that's more like retail
i want to throw my money on
yeah it's like you go to a casino
and you throw your chip on red right
it's the same right
you have a one percent move
you get wiped out
most professional traders
actually trade to 2x
maybe most 5x
really you got to think of
going back to the example of trade
like this tool actually if you use it well
it can actually result in better
what's called in finance
risk adjusted returns
what that means is
for the same amount of risk
i'm i have higher returns
because i'm using leverage in a good way
and i'll explain that in a second
or for the same return
maybe i don't know 10
i am having less risk
because i'm using leverage in a good way
and a really quick example is
stocks and bonds
going back to traditional finance
i think most people know what those are
so like you what you buy stocks
because they're higher risk
and they're higher return
so i don't know you make nine percent
return on average on the s&p 500
but if you buy bonds that are lower risk
so the idea is people that are old
buy bonds
and if you're young you buy stuff
and bonds low risk means i don't know
you make three four percent
on the same amount of capital
so now like if i'm an investor
i i want to hold both
but i'm not going to hold bonds
if my goal is nine percent return
i'm not going to do that
but what does that mean
it means that on a year that bonds
do really bad i get wrecked
and i would have loved to hold
old bonds
so this goes to diversification right
so how can i diversify in a way
where essentially i have exposure to both
but i still getting the nine percent return
you can use leverage
you can risk adjust the bonds
so you buy a hundred dollars of stocks
and then you buy
so then you buy your leverage
a hundred dollars of bonds
and what that does is that
you're in fact you actually buy more
than a hundred dollars
because it has some higher volatility
but basically the point is
you you increase your allocation to bonds
on leverage
so you're amplifying the bonds return
and what that does is yes
part of your portfolio is levered up
but actually your risk is lower
because essentially they're both targeting the same return
but they're diversified
so on a year that bonds do well
you know stocks might be terrible
and vice versa
and your long-term return is nine percent
i'm getting too much in traditional finance
but that's like one one thing
a little bit of leverage
allows you to achieve this right
a little like a little bit of something is
it tends to be good
a lot of it tends to just like wreck you
in every possible way right
finish up
leverage is present in the everyday world
so give me a couple of really practical examples
the first that comes to mind is mortgages
i buy a home
i borrow from the bank
i put down 20 percent
i don't know much incident in taiwan
but in america for example it's 20 percent
that means that the bank gives me the other 80 percent
i'm levered five to one
i have a 5x levered position
leverage position
which is collateralized by my home
but that is leverage
it's 5x by the way
so it's not very little
now another practical example
if i buy yes like a stock
an american stock in the s&p 500
apple or google or whatever right
like i have leverage
even though there is no like
trading on leverage
perhaps no no
you know fancy instrument
that i'm using
i am levered
and the reason why i'm levered
is because the average company
in the s&p 500
is his levered itself
2x
so i didn't know that
yes yes
they have there
they have leverage themselves right
can you touch on
why is it levered 2x
oh it's very simple
it's your balance sheet right
so like your mind
your amount of some
essentially your
your total assets are 2x
of your net worth
so like they have
they borrowed some amount
right from the banks and so on
right right right
wow yeah
so everything is levered really
yeah and what do you think
the financial crisis happened
in 2008
because these banks were taking
an insane amount of leverage
right so yeah
well so they got rex
so now talking about leverage
we want to talk about futures
right a lot of people in crypto
they trade futures
and why does it exist
perpetual is what you're referring to
crypto they are essentially
the equivalent of the future
the difference is the future is dated
perpetual is not
which is kind of like a great
innovation of crypto
futures exist
really came into existence
because it's really important
to think about derivatives
in terms of like
two players right
two people that are taking
different leg of the
of that position right
so on one side you have a speculator
which is a person essentially
which is not necessarily a bad term
right people think oh
it's speculative you're bad
you're not bad you're just
taking bets you have like a view
and you want to make money and you want to take leverage on your view right
it's fine
actually you have if the economic system where you're where you're trading
is well designed essentially you're actually
really important functioning piece of it because you're providing liquidity
so you have a speculator on one side
and on the second side essentially you have a hedger an investor
like essentially a risk taker
and a risk reducer right
that's the way you need to think about these instruments
now back in the days this started with farmers
i kind of like knew what the price of corn was right now
but i my harvest would happen in six months a year or whatever right
i would have to plan right there's some financial planning and say okay you
know i'm assuming that you know i'm selling i don't know like
a hundred dollars a bushel whatever it's called
i would need to plan with that in mind right
now the price of corn at the time of the harvest of selling
might change might go up or might go down right
so if if it goes down i could potentially get wrecked and i would fail
my business would fail and it would be over
they invented this instrument called the future where essentially you could as a
corn farmer you could hedge you have to set aside by going short
the future which means you would lock in a price which also meant that if it went
up you would not make that amount they went up but it didn't matter for you
because you planned on margins right you say okay i can make this margin and you
want a stability right so you were taking off risk the table right
on the other side who was taking the other side of the position someone who
believed the price would actually go up right so speculator so that's kind of
like why they invented futures originally and i think it's the chicago board of
trade that started that in america you said crypto market the capital is
inefficient what do you mean by that going going back to this to this concept
this idea of of hedging and you know like in crypto you have
thresholds and in crypto essentially you have people that are like you know
trades for thresholds you're not and then you're going longer
threshold you're going short the perp what i meant to say is that there is a
lot of speculation and there's not enough hedging or like reducing risk that's
that's kind of like what what i meant right and and you see this a lot more i would
say there's a big difference also between uh centralized exchanges and d5 um
in centralized exchanges you have really uh the big innovation that ftx brought to
the market before they blew up was this concept of a sub account so they didn't
really invent anything new they just took what existed in traditional finance
which is brokerage accounts that are capital efficient and they replicated it in
crypto it just means that for the first time you could actually have this
account where you would deposit any token bitcoin ethereum whatever they would all act as
collateral and then you'll be able to open per positions with that collateral it's
not not just with stable point that give you this massive capital efficiency where
essentially the purpose will be what's called cross margin so the pnl of one perp
could be used as collateral for a second the bottom line is that if you were on the
other side of the hedging side you were doing this thing that ethena does the basis
trade that's very famous right now you were like an investor that was hedging risk and
you were getting really good adjust risk adjuster return you doing that it was
translating a lower funding rate so if you were a speculator you were getting essentially also
really really good funding rates that allow you to to speculate at a lower cost which is what you
want as a speculator what are some common ways to hedge in trend five or crypto in crypto one way
we discussed this is basis trade another thing is delta neutral strategies which i would argue they
don't really exist in centralized exchanges this is an opportunity i think just for define
explain in defi essentially you can actually hold what are called lsts lsds depending on who's calling
it liquid staking derivatives liquid staking tokens this is essentially as if you're holding you know
if you have ethereum you know and you don't want to forego the the staking yield you can actually
deposit this in lido for example and you can hold st and so like and then what it does it accrues the
yield that specifically rebases but that's the point you you have this liquid stake version of ethereum and
you can hold it and and it moves like ethereum but it also accrues on top essentially the yield
which is great because you can use it in d5 protocols as collateral when you have this in d5
now what you can do you can actually do really cool things if you have the capital efficiency that we
discussed where essentially you can deposit into an account your sd and then you could go short the
perk for the same amount what that will do is it will remove completely the ethereum exposure and
now you're getting risk-free close to risk-free like delta neutral you get athena plus
the staking yield basically right that's one example then you have other examples you can do
you can do levered lending so if i'm on ave and i'm lending essentially let's say atom right you're
getting 15 apr which is pretty attractive but you don't really care about you know the atom volatility
you don't want it you just want 15 and maybe you even want that on leverage but so same concept you
deposit it into mars you hold it you're getting 15 you go short the perp and all of a sudden you're
getting 15 plus the funding rate right these are great hedging what i call investor opportunities
right you're as an investor you're coming in and you're just like getting really good at risk
adjusted return in crypto and trad fi there's other things you can do it's contraptionally
similar you can what you do is if you want to if you buy a government bond on an emerging market
for example like for example i don't know turkey and it's in us dollars you don't really want to get
exposure to what's called the nominal rates underneath you just want the credit risk exposure right you
just want that five additional five percent that you'll get over the government us government bonds so
what you do is you buy that you on leverage you essentially borrow the us government bond you
short it and then you do this what's called duration adjusted that's that's the term and then you then
you isolate just that what's called risk premium you just like that you can do the same with equities
you can you can essentially maybe just give you an example you're bullish nvidia pretty priced
in already but you're bullish even more and you want to essentially go short the sector you want
to isolate that stock right but you don't you want to protect yourself from like a market downturn
a broader market downturn right so what do you do you go along buy essentially nvidia and then you
essentially go short the sector and you have to adjust this by a little bit and that will do what
we'll do is that since nvidia essentially supposed to do better for you than the sector then you'll
just isolate that component that which then you can also lever up by using government bonds but the
point is it's like you can hedge out things and then make specific bets or reduce risk on one side
mind blown do you know what this feels like it feels like i'm watching harry potter it's like you're
doing all these cool stuff and i'm like wow that makes a lot of sense that's just like what hedge
funds do and then yeah professional traders do yeah do you hedge differently in crypto and bull
markets and bear market this is the part where we say it's not investment advice that's it is still not
investment do your own research so the concepts are the same when you abstract away from like the
mechanics the concepts are the same you're just you're oscillating your risk premium or you're essentially
reducing a specific amount of risk but what i would say is this when there is a bull market what generally
happens is let's talk from an investor perspective you don't really care about essentially holding
a specific asset because you're you don't want to speculate that you just we just want to get the
best risk adjusted return so from a investor perspective which is where hedging comes in
for the most part if you think about it during a bull market people are more bullish so what that
translates into is higher funding rate so people are just going to want to take more crazier bets on
bitcoin ethereum and all these like what that translates to do into like it's higher funding rates which means
that if you do the carry trade which arguably you can do through like on sd eth and bc you can do
three tina on ethereum you'll be able to do it in a much cleaner and simpler way but the point is like
really high higher risk adjusted returns ultimately you'll get a higher yield for roughly the same
amount of risk so that's that's what you can do during a bull market if you're an investor now if you
are doing a bear market what happens during the bear market people like are more risk adverse so you'll
start seeing a lot of a lot of flight to safety the crypto equivalent to that so that translates into
people just converting their their tokens in stables depositing the stables in the money market and
then the money market you'll see this the money market like apr for those tables like lend apr just
goes down like a lot right even even below like the us risk free rate which is a little crazy so then
what do you do in that case right actually in that case leverage through margin what's called margin
which means you're essentially borrowing usdc and you're essentially buying stuff on leverage becomes
actually cheaper so you can actually do this same basis trade but you can actually do it on leverage
you already are doing a leverage because shorting the purpose leverage you can amplify that even more
by essentially given that your return is going to drop because the funding rate is going to drop maybe
it drops from 30 to i don't know five ten percent like you can amplify this because what what you do is
you borrow usdc and maybe you're paying on three percent and you increase your position on i don't know is
it is it adam or whatever it is you need to you adjust it right like you know when when it's the bull you
don't need to use additional leverage and when it's not a bull you can essentially like use usdc as
leverage additional leverage to amplify the return that's one thing you could do but mars is doing is
building essentially a vault protocol sitting on top of mars where essentially anybody can come in
and build these vaults third-party vaults some are going to be like users with reputation building so
some of them are going to have the basis trade you can just go in and open that vault see it and just do
it that way so kind of like an automated vault that essentially you can go in you can deposit your
assets and your tokens and stables and essentially doing getting the same thing as a professional
trader would do with a basis trade what mars does remember this we discussed about the sub accounts
right in trading in centralized exchanges is taking this concept yeah and replicating it in decentralized
finance under a new primitive money label essentially which is called the credit account and this credit
account essentially replicates what you have you know in the sub accounts it gives you the same
capital efficiency which means you can hold any token as collateral as long as it's on chain right
as collateral you can take any proposition they're cross margin they're cross collateralized but it goes
beyond that that it's even better than a centralized exchange because unlike a centralized exchange you can
hold specific d5 primitives that only exist in d5 as collateral so you know for example you need to
swap pools lps in our case we don't have us what we have like astroport which i actually think is
better because i believe passive concentrated liquidity is better we so have holding that as
collateral in your account so essentially if i want to you know i want to ape in some you know lp pool
providing liquidity in a good way like with passive concentrated liquidity but i want to use that
as collateral to take on a per position i don't want to exit because i want to bet on bitcoin you can
deposit on mars and you can open a bitcoin long position lp of vaults can be at can act as collateral any
any primitive connective collateral on mars but it's actually more than that because the account
is a primitive but it's a money legal right so you can actually build stuff using the account
the right around the top of mars and so that's the innovation so it's really thought from the ground up
with this concept of capital efficiency and extensibility you talked about hedging earlier
right how do i hedge on marsh protocol it's the simplest thing in the world it's like one click and
you do it really so yeah it's simple you have a we have a credit account you want to do the basis trade
two like really two clicks and it's done right you just you go in you go on mars you deposit i don't
know wste which is available on train on neutron you just deposit it actually you don't need to do
it you deposit usdc on mars you're coming from ethereum you deposit usdc through cctp it should be
pretty seamless then it will mint for you an account in the background you don't even know and now you see
that you have usdc then one action deposit second action you go in you essentially swap that usdc
for wste third action you short the perp for the same exact amount and you're done you're collecting
the basis trade now you're hedging out you guys have been around for a long time many many years
and you are a part of tara ecosystem right and of course we all know the ecosystem collapsed but you
survived and you worked through and tell us the story i was sort of saying that i wasn't part of the
original mars team i joined which you know were the number one contributors for mars for mars protocol
and but i was there i literally joined and after weeks three weeks so what did the collapse occurred
it was it was rough because keep in mind like everybody had a lot of capital their personal
capital and wealth they saw it completely wiped these were contributors that like they had locked
tokens right they didn't really yeah they didn't see it at all and they lost massive figures i imagine
myself i was an investor in tara and i and i had quite a bit so you had that stress going on top of
that like the people were getting liquidated people like you know there was just like a total mayhem
right they just needed to support the thing so they they were making sure that the protocol was
working fine and people were getting liquidated orderly and all that people would want to get out
winning it out on top of that there was a lock drop which means that people had their money locked
in so like they just really quickly tried to for governance of course because you know that's the
right way to kind of like unlock the liquidity so people would just get it they were just like
working over hours doing insane things with the stress on top of like what was happening which was
clearly not the fault and then on top of that when all that happened we were like we just took a step
back and we were like we tried to look at it objectively so what's our next step i mean
clearly the first thing that comes to mind is where's the liquidity ethereum layer two is ethereum
layer one so like a lot of projects from tara did that under labs like you know delphi has a great
research arm and it's what to me one of the top research companies in in crypto so we talked to the
researchers we we you know looked into the what we call the hive mind and we did research okay what is the
best place to go and we ended up going full circle that cosmos was the best place
for us to go for a variety of reasons and then we looked at our vision and we said okay where's
the vision of mars what do we want mars to be in the long term term best place to trade on to
trading crypto for leverage rival centralized exchanges experience and even better make it even better
that's the goal let's go build this basically just to build on what you just said so choosing
the chain or ecosystem to build your project on is like choosing which country you want to build your
company right for example if a chain has a very large total value lock then that means this
country is probably very rich and it's good for business so with that logic and with the story
you just told us why did you choose cosmos why didn't you pick for example ee clearly the the most
attractive thing that you can think of when you're building is where is the tbl where is where the
users where is the tbl yeah and again most a lot of people did that and that's a way to go but when
you do that you have to be conscious of the fact that it's not going to scale in a good way so if
ultimately your what is your goal you could consciously say well i'm going to go on a chain
where on a layer two right there's a lot of tvl that can attract more users more tl and then what's
the mid to long-term game right because you know that you're going to go there you're going to have
to leave at one point and the reason is because for a d5 protocol it's not scalable in the same way
it's not just scalability and it's configurability you don't have that in the same way that you would
have it with an action so you're not really sovereign that's the word to use in crypto you're not
sovereign and that is actually extremely important for a d5 protocol because it's not just about
sharing block space which is the problem to an extent could be a problem it's not necessarily a
problem but it's also like you need these customizations that are just good for you or
for other d5 protocols which the chain is not going to give you or they're not going to respond to you
right so so the reason why dydx left for example ethereum world and they went and built their own cosmos
chains is exactly that sovereign sovereign ability the ability to be sovereign to make to adjust their
chain in a way that essentially allows them to build the product that they want to build the
vision that they have they're like really chain agnostic they're just like we want this product
we want to be the best product possible how do we get there we need to be sovereign that was the
reason because then they can customize it in a way with the off-chain order book you know with
with all these things you know that that they're useful for them so in d5 you really need control of
your stack to build a product that in the mid to long term allows you to be successful and achieve the
scale if you have a vision of a product it really boils down to you know your vision
on what do you think a great product should be to me the vision that i have is not too different
than anybody the x guys have it's like you ultimately you're building a product and your
user goes to your product because you have an awesome ideally the user it goes to mars protocol
for example doesn't even know that it's on neutron chain right just comes in like through ccdp like uses
like you know our android wallet for example or use metamask right and it's just like okay great that kind
of experience where essentially you're going to the product you're coming from a tier you're coming from
from a centralized exchange and you don't even know you're there you're the expert i want to ask you
how do you maximize or optimize the profit on mars you need to give an example i'm bullish bitcoin i
get non-investment advice i'm bullish bitcoin but i'm not bullish between the next year for your reasons
we can talk more about that you know i can either ape in a certain amount of money directly and buy btc
right you can do that on mars by the way you just buy btc wbtc so which by the way is issued natively in
cosmos the same way that it is issued natively on ethereum so you're getting the same experience the same risk
but you you buy it right and you hold it but that's you know like is that really attractive
because i do want to take some leverage i think bitcoin has this lower bought as a lower potential
than these altcoins right yeah so what do i do i can buy a perp go two three x leverage which is could be
reasonable right but the question is do you want to do that because that means you're you're taking on
a negative funding rate for the next year which means like it's probably going to eat in your returns by
30 or 50 right or even more it's probably not the right way of doing that so the right way if you have
essentially this like mid to long term view is to use margin which means you can essentially you
borrow stables and with that so you deposit bitcoin you borrow usdc and you increase and you swap it
for bitcoin and you get like two three x leverage people do this manually through money markets like
av and so on on mars you can do this with one click margin trading one click basically so that's what
i do for example because i'm you know bullish bitcoin the next year you can now see bitcoin with
three thousand dollars but no no that's one way another way if you're short term you want to you want to
place bets you you just like open per positions another thing you can do is these vaults you can
deposit into these vaults and another thing that you can do is with the drop launch which is a really
big catalyst that's happening on neutron which is the train where mars is is built on drop essentially is
a an liquid sticking derivative protocol but this one is particularly interesting because it is backed by
lido so lido is the number one tv hell for like you know d5 protocol on encryptor part of the drop launch
there's going to be a points campaign they call them droplets and you'll be able to go on mars
and farm these points with leverage and some of these opportunities are going to be dealt unusual
opportunities so you can just go in and just get isolated exposure to the points and there's going
to be probably vaults that are going to be built that you just ape in and you just farm the points
basically you don't even need to understand how to do it manually okay anything else that you want
to tell us about what you're currently working on or which stage this project is at we essentially
have this v2 launch we call it v2 launch where essentially we're going to have this credit
accounts on neutron we'll have this third-party vault protocol built on top it's going to be i
think one of the best experiences in in d5 then we'll launch a public test net for perps as well while
this is happening we'll also do that and it's going to be an incentivized test net where you can come
in and if you find bugs there's going to be a bugs bounty you'll get rewarded in mars we're also
going to have a competition top trader that makes the most money the highest pnl will get we'll get
awarded mars trader that gets the worst pnl you get wrecked go and get wrecked as much as you can you'll
get rewarded the same amount as a top trader ideally we haven't figured out the math yet but it's going
to be i want the same guy that gets liquidated so really the one-to-one the number one guy that gets
wrecked in practice we'll get pay we'll get mars and so on right it's going to be an interesting and fun
competition people just like heavily using perps on mars and then finding uncovering bugs vulnerabilities
and then things like that and then we'll launch first basically see that will really unlock
the capital efficiency thing that we discussed basically of course we want to talk about your
mars token mars token trades right now on two cosmos chains for the most part one is osmosis then the
second trainer we're on is neutron which essentially which is really where we're building our deep product
there you have these two chains where you can trade more i wouldn't be too surprised that if it starts
getting traded also on centralized exchanges the tokenomics on mars how we're changing or revamping it
because we used to have an old tokenomics that that came from the teraday so mars really the way it
worked was after the teraday thing happened we really wanted to make good our community a lot of
projects that just like you know relaunched the token completely from scratch we didn't do that we
essentially airdropped to previous mars holders the token we wanted to make people good okay so on top
of that when we launched we had like a mars chain that you know because we had this view that we wanted
to get different chains and essentially have an orchestration layer through a chain and then that didn't turn
out to be the right decision because we realized quickly that to achieve the best product possible
we really need to focus on one chain where we believe we could achieve it in the fast in the
fastest way and go deep really deep in features so like this thing didn't work so we decided to retire
the hub our chain and instead like transition the token through to to neutron so which essentially
is going to be the the chain where token exists we had a massive community pool we decided to burn
significant amount because we didn't need it anymore to incentivize the validators so essentially
like the amount of supply total supply is actually a lot lower than it used to be because of that
that's just recently happened so what we're doing is we're gonna essentially the the protocol revenue
that will come through perhaps trading fees borrow fees and liquidation part of it will go essentially
to a buy and burn where essentially we'll buy mars from the from the pool on on neutron will burn it
and part of it will go to and buy an lp this is kind of like what maker does over time we'll keep
deepening liquidity on chain so that's the token model in terms of utility itself of the token there's
really two things one was already voted in the same proposal which is going to be fee not rebates
fee discount if you're an active trader you can actually stake mars and your fees get reduced
significantly depending on how much you stake or if you're a vault builder and you want your vault
apr to go up you can actually stake mars in your vault and your apr is going to go up because your
fees are going to get lower that's the main utility of the token there's going to be a second
utility that we're going to that we're talking about suggesting and governance to vote on probably
later in 2025 which is yield opportunities some yield opportunities are going to be limited we're
going to have things like 7x leverage on leverage stake it's going to fill up really fast because
if you're getting 100 apr you know like 90 apr people are going to want to happen how do we create
value for this car city we'll do that for staking okay any alpha you can tell us so i would say first
of all one piece of alpha the the way our perps works it's uh it's oracle based perps so they traded
the oracle price there's no order book which means people can just come in and trade and they won't get
wrecked like on these other order books chains that don't have any activity kind of like it happens
with synthetics or you know gmx and all that but in our model essentially we have a counterparty vault
model it's it's not fully funded it's counterparty so essentially for us so you deposit usdc and you're
essentially allowing this this perplot model to work you're deposited into this counterparty vault
and you get an epr we're going to incentivize that through mars so when we launch it late august
you'll be able to open and get you know like pretty i think pretty pretty good amount of mars through
that it's one piece of i would call alpha and then i would say more it was more interesting it's
coming up towards the end of the year and 2025 we're going to try to create really really cool
visualizations and calculations on on pnl so we really want to be like a professional trader
platform where essentially you go in and you see like your breakdown how much money you made on
this position like how much money you made in your account so like we're really going to try to
bring stuff that i haven't seen even in centralized exchanges that i know from that i've seen all in
trad fi try to take those good practices and replicate them in crypto so you actually have a
really good breakdown and and you can actually make better informed decisions since you work in
trad fi in this crypto bull run we see institutions coming in like for example bitcoin etf and then now
it's ethereum etf do you think this bull run will look different from our previous forums so crypto is
clearly a risky asset it's way more risky in stocks and so then you have this massive liquidity
that just like runs up to crypto and then you get like these crazy storing prices and
it creates momentum and people come in and retail oh look look you know like boden is up 300 so then
they just start aping in so we are not really there yet inflation is still quite high and from a
fundamental perspective we can go why ultimately energy prices are high but the point is is like
it's not a favorable environment for high risk stuff you know like things are happening and then and
and you know the central bank softened up on the tightening so it really depends on how that's going
to go i think from a macroeconomic perspective and also there's there's a regulatory risk in the us most
likely chance that that will occur that there are a couple of things that could happen right one
thing could be the regulatory perspective gets better for crypto and that is a good great growth
catalyst imagine like being able to open up defi to america because right now for example if
you're if you're using mars protocol you're like in your new united states it's blocked we try to
avoid americans from using mars because it's just not a favorable environment for defi right there
but if it becomes favorable it's the number one market in the world then the second one i would say is
energy prices from my personal opinion if they drop significantly then you see also inflation in
my opinion to drop significantly from what you just said what i heard is you think this is not the bull
market yet am i correct i don't think so i think it is a bull market i think that the bull can be
much more of a bull like if we get favorable conditions which is rates dropping in my opinion
and the fire regulation these are could be great catalysts in my opinion i think it's really
interesting how you know bitcoin has 4x since like the local low and then people still think
this is not really a bull market because we want to see everything go up like that's yeah that
craziness is what we define a bull market right crypto it makes sense because the volatility is
really the risk is extremely yeah so you you're expecting much higher return i would also add people
talk about etfs but really it's not open to retail yet it's not if you are like a retail investor and you
are in america and you want to ape in for example the blackrock etf i bet i think it's called you can't
many platforms don't allow you to do that they say it's too risky blah blah and and some people are
transferring their assets away but most people are going to be okay fine whatever when that happens
that opens up quite a bit of opportunity right but that doesn't happen yet there's an etf but it's
mostly institutions it's actually careful institutions right so so they're just still like a long way
there to go i think when people start aping in like you said usually it means the local top is here
right and then that's probably when you should leave the market how do you define people aping in a top
signal could have been like this guy who called me and is like oh you know i'm i i wanna you know when
i'm buying dodge coin because you know it's backed by elon musk that was kind of like pretty strong
signal i think the truth is the last the the signal there was the collapse of terra like right that was
the stick and then the continuous collapse of the things the other things that were lined up behind
it what are some categories you think will do very well in this ball and why so the narrative of this
bull cycle has been in my opinion has been two things one is the meme coin they've been doing like
you know crazy volatility it's it's literally like it's like a ponzi scheme right like you come in
earlier you make money you get everyone it has no intrinsic value right now people are kind of like
gonna hate me for this but it's it's true people are tired of being seeing like there's like the
liquidity for like and so this is kind of like their reaction then the other thing that's been
doing really well is still like layer one you look at these launches like you know celestia and you know
and there's gonna be others that are launched i would say that it's just saying it's just an
example of layer ones are coming out the other one that's being quite quite a phenomenal has been
a tina like this business trade thing which to me is really not decentralized it's a great product
so undoubtedly right and they did done really well and i think they're gonna do even better so kind of like
the narrative a lot of them have gone toward towards this like real yield type of thing which
to me doesn't make sense the reason why doesn't make sense is because i'm not in crypto to make 10
on a volatile token i am not i'm in crypto to make 10 20 30 like you know x whatever it is not me but
average person and so like if you're giving me stable yield i don't care much better of a product
where essentially you know like it's going to go back into a buyback or something that will pump the
token i think some of these guys are going to understand this i hope and then they'll readjust
their tokenomics as they grow and maybe they change their tokenomics they can be they can
potentially become attractive but i think there's another narrative which is more attractive it's
interesting is the the merging of crypto and ai is this kind of narrative which people say it's a
little bit self-fulfilling which is basically you know that ai agents are going to be the number one
crypto users and all that i think it's true though it's true because it's simpler for an ai agent to
like actually use crypto as a means of exchange of value and store value that's a big narrative the
question is how far can that go you know what are the use cases and all that but that's something
that i think the next big narrative i think a lot of ai tokens though they're more like meme coins like
at this stage right how do you identify which one is actually valuable investment to make you need to
see who's building towards those use cases what the team is right how much they've raised who's backing
them and then you know like what their roadmap is if they can share it like for example mars can't
share for legal reasons but some people do so like i think that you need to do your research and see
who has the best backing and who essentially is actually executing towards the thing that you think
are the proper use cases that will generate value what is your personal investment strategy for this
bull run how are you planning on making the most out of it a big believer in the separation of the
beta from the alpha of investing is the traditional finance advice it's not investment advice so
essentially when they look when you look at your wealth they'll say okay you need to have a
certain amount in your safety fund your rainy day fund generally it's like six to 12 months of your
month expenses you put that aside and you put that in in cash then the remaining you need to invest you
should invest 80 to 90 percent of that into a beta portfolio right and i'll talk to explain to you
something what that means 10 to 20 percent just do alpha right now the beta means essentially passive
long-term investment strategies that will generate value over time let's call the 60 40 outside
location model these are like the vanguard target fund and then essentially 10 to 20 percent of your
portfolio it's alpha and alpha is just bets it's just like things that you think are going to achieve
value and you are okay potentially losing all of it so it's just your personal views i look at crypto
as my alpha portfolio so what do i do there right like there's different things that you can do for me
i like personally i like to hold blue chips levered i like bitcoin and ethereum levered with margin because
it doesn't wreck me right not with burps i tend to not have like short-term views i tend to have like
mid to long-term views which is crypto is like six months here and then on the other side i have
a look at yield opportunity opportunities in d5 so things like i don't know pendle and i also there's
a lot of opportunities also with just like stables like right now during the bull like
some stables are going up like 15 20 that's kind of way to look at it i think you might have answered
the next question though but i want to ask you again so how do you pick and choose your crypto or your
token is it different from let's say a person that's crypto native some of the things are the
same so there's some similarities i generally don't like to besides the blue chips which are
conditions right the ones the specific token bets in this 20 alpha that we discussed i don't like to
pick things that i don't understand when i'm buying individual tokens i try to understand essentially
if it's something that i would try to use it if i like it i try to look at the roadmap the team and all
that and and if essentially to me it's undervalued i buy it that's what i do but again i don't
have a big portion of portfolio in that so on the yield opportunity side i think it's trying to
understand what the risk is what platform it is on what's the track record how many hacks you know
like what is the risk adjusted potential return you know what cut are you taking and so i think it's
probably different because i'm really like i try to think always from a risk perspective but there's
something different in crypto that tread 5 doesn't have which is people using nft or like the team is
anonymous do you try to avoid that type of project question is like are they really anonymous
they're anonymous to you that they're not really putting their names and things behind it but like
why don't you take a look at who's invested in them if it's institutional level bc they're definitely
not anonymous so they're anonymous to you and to the public but they're not because the bc essentially
knows who they are so if if something happens to the team they they you know they run away with the
money whatever it is you know first of all they have the bcs that to deal with i would be careful
if it's not bc funded or if it's just like this project out there and you don't know who they are and all
that thank you very much that was very insightful a great conversation thank you appreciate it really
really thank you so much for for you know having resisted this long if you have definitely follow
mars protocol i'm excited to have you guys on mars